A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Board of Nursing, xxxx-xxxx.
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Virginia Board of Nursing,
xxxx-xxxx.
The Library of Virginia
xxxxx
Virginia. Dept. of Health Professions.
xx cu. ft.
Administrative Information
Arranged chronologically.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions
Acquisition Information
Accession 45475 was transferred by the Dept. of Health Professions on 4/7/2011.
Historical Information
The Board of Examiners of Graduate Nurses was created by an act of Assembly May 1, 1903 to regulate the professional nursing of the sick in Virginia. The Board examined applicants, issued licenses and held the power to revoke licenses. At some point the name of the Board was changed to the Board of Examiners of Nurses. An act of Assembly dated March 17, 1970 created the Board of Nursing and repealed the chapter of the Code authorizing the Board of Examiners of Nurses. The new board has similar responsibilites, also including the accreditation of nursing curricula and promulgation of regulations.
The Dept. of Health Regulatory Boards was created by an act passed by the General Assembly on March 31, 1977, to provide administrative services to the health regulatory boards of the state. The boards continue to regulate their professions through the examination, licensing, and disciplining of the practitioners of health science. In 1986, the Dept. of Health Regulatory Boards became the Dept. of Health Professions. Its mission is to enhance the delivery of safe and competent health care by licensing qualified health care professionals, enforcing standards of practice, and providing information to both practitioners and consumers of health care services.
Scope and Content
Records, xxxx-xxxx, include Registers of registered nurses, 1908-1977; Register of certified tuberculosis nurses, 1926-1941.
Contents List
- Records of the Virginia Board of Nursing, 1908-1977.
  - Licensing fee books, 1950-1971 (Accession 30215)., Extent: 3 v.
    Licensing fee books include monthly totals for licensure renewals.
    - Licensing fee book, 1950-1959. (Volume 1)
    - Licensing fee book, 1960-1965. (Volume 2)
    - Licensing fee book, 1965-1971. (Volume 3)
  - Register of certified tuberculosis nurses, 1926-1941 (Accession 30215)., Extent: 1 v.
    Register of certified tuberculosis nurses includes certificate number, date issued, name, and training school.
    - Register, 1926-1941. (Volume 1)
  - Registers of registered nurses, 1908-1977 (Accession 30215)., Extent: 7 v.
    Registers of registered nurses include certificate number, date issued, name, training school and location, date of graduation, and remarks. Each volume is arranged alphabetically.
    - Register, 1909-1918. (Volume 1)
    - Register (Certificates 1-4527), 1908-1927. (Volume 2)
    - Register (Certificates 4528-18567), 1928-1951. (Volume 3)
    - Register (Certificates 18568-30904), 1952-1962. (Volume 4)
    - Register (Certificates 30905-41240), 1963-1968. (Volume 5)
    - Register (Certificates 41241-51244), 1969-1972. (Volume 6)
    - Register (Certificates 51245-64168), 1973-1977. (Volume 7)
  - Register of licensed practical nurses, 1963-1972 (Accession 30215)., Extent: 1 v.
    Register of licensed practical nurses include license number, date issued, name, practical nurse school attended and location, and remarks. Includes certificates #7474-17527.
    - Register, 1963-1972. (Volume 1)
  - Register of averages of nurse candidates for registration, 1903-1953 (Accession 30215)., Extent: 3 v.
    Registers include name and grades in the areas of anatomy, bacteriology, chemistry, contagious/infection diseases, dietetics, ethics, hygiene, medical nursing, obstetrical nursing, pediatrics, physiology, practical nursing, surgical nursing and urinalysis.
    - Register, 1903-1927. (Volume 1)
    - Register, 1928-1945. (Volume 2)
    - Register, 1945-1953. (Volume 3)
  - Audit reports, 1920-1927 (Accession 30215)., Extent: 1 v.
    Includes financial statements and correspondence.
    - Audit reports, 1920-1927. (Volume 1)
  - Examination questions, 1911-1927 (Accession 37954)., Extent: 1 v.
    Includes lists of questions on the topics of anatomy, bacteriology, chemistry, contagious/infection diseases, dietetics, ethics, hygiene, medical nursing, obstetrical nursing, pediatrics, physiology, practical nursing, surgical nursing and urinalysis.
    - Minutes, 1959 July 6. (Volume 1)
  - Advisory Council on Nursing Training, 1958-1966 (Accession 30215)., Extent: 1 cu. ft.
    Records include minutes, agendas, budgets, correspondence, manuals, publications, questionnaires, reports, and surveys.
    - Minutes, 1959 July 6. (Volume 1)
    - Minutes, 1959 July 29. (Volume 1)
    - Minutes, 1959 Dec 2. (Volume 1)
    - Minutes, 1960 Feb 19. (Volume 1)
    - Minutes, 1960 July 27. (Volume 1)
    - Meeting records, 1965 Sept 22. (Volume 1)
    - Corresponence - Meeting, 1960 Feb 19. (Volume 1)
    - Correspondence - Meeting, 1960 July 27. (Volume 1)
    - Correspondence, 1960 Jan-1961 Apr. (Volume 1)
    - Correspondence, 1961-1964. (Volume 1)
    - Correspondence - Miscellaneous, 1958-1960. (Volume 1)
    - Correspondence - Miscellaneous, 1961-1964 June. (Volume 1)
    - Correspondence - Miscellaneous, 1964 June-Dec. (Volume 1)
    - Corresponence - Miscellaneous, 1965. (Volume 1)
    - Correspondence - Miscellaneous, 1966. (Volume 1)
    - DePaul Hospital (Norfolk), 1958-1960. (Volume 1)
    - Leigh Memorial Hospital (Norfolk), 1958-1960. (Volume 1)
    - Lynchburg Memorial Hospital, 1958-1961. (Volume 1)
    - Preparation for public hearing, 1959. (Volume 1)
    - Program chart, undated. (Volume 1)
    - Questionnaires, 1965. (Volume 1)
    - Questionnaires, 1965. (Volume 1)
    - Questionnaires (no state aid), 1965. (Volume 1)